How can a mitochondrial protein found
inside your kidneys cause kidney
failure? Well, we'll find out. But
beyond that, there are multiple things,
including a shunned supplement that can
help prevent all the kidney chaos. As
your kidneys filter all the molecules in
your blood to keep them or dispose of
them, your kidneys use a lot of energy
to fulfill that function. And I don't
know if you've heard the word going
around the block, but uh the
mitochondria
It's the powerhouse of the cell. That
includes kidney cells or if you want to
get professional, renal cells. So to
support that energy production,
predictably mitochondria have to be
spitting out mass amounts of cellular
energy known as ATP. And in fact, many
mitochondrial genes are associated with
kidney function. However, one critically
important protein in mitochondria called
TFAM dramatically reduces the kidney's
ability to generate energy through
mitochondria when it's missing. In fact,
we see that here from this big study
looking at the relationship. This is in
animals missing TFAM in red at different
time points. We're seeing cellular
energy. Remember that's ATP. Clearly
both conditions with TFAM missing called
knockout indicate reduced cellular
energy. And in human kidneys there is a
simple association between lower TFAM
levels and worse kidney function. So not
definitive but certainly suggestive
considering the relationship that we're
about to uncover. But what exactly does
TFAM do? I mean why is it leading to a
significant reduction in our cell's
ability to generate energy? It actually
does multiple things, but the title
doesn't include leaking mitochondria
without reason. And it has to do with
the functions of TFAM. TFAM folds and
stabilizes mitochondrial genes by
holding on to the mitochondrial DNA
inside of our mitochondrian that
protects the DNA from damage, but also
stabilizes it for it to be read by gene
reading machinery and produced into
functional mitochondrial proteins. So
it's critically important for healthy
mitochondria. But for some reason the
researchers showed that a loss of
mitochondrial TFAM in the kidney leads
to increased encroachment of immune
cells cysts bubbling up in the kidney
and kidney cells dying. So what's going
on here? Well, it starts with this.
We're looking at measure of
mitochondrial DNA found in the cytool.
Okay, if you don't know what that means,
your cells are split between different
compartments. Most of your genes are
held in the nucleus except for a small
amount found in the mitochondria. The
point being, they're supposed to stay
there. So, if they're in the space
outside of those two compartments, like
the cytool, that's a big alarm bell. So,
let's try that again. We're looking at a
measure of mitochondrial DNA. The higher
the bars go up, the more DNA is found in
the cytosol.un.
I'm glad we could share that anxiety
together. So, the green bars indicate
more mitochondrial DNA is leaking out of
the mitochondria into the space that
it's not supposed to be. Poorly
functioning kidneys can be poorly
functioning because of low
concentrations of TFAM protein found
inside the mitochondria which leads to
mitochondria genes leaking out of the
mitochondrian. That is the trigger for
the invasion of immune cells, kidney
cysts and kidneys dying. That's the sum
of it. But there's a puzzle piece still
missing. How do we go from leaking
mitochondria to all hell breaking loose
in and around the kidney cells, the
renal cells if I might? Cytoolic or in
another term outside the mitochondria
DNA gets bound by a protein called CGA
or Cass, which then activates a whole
string of communication proteins within
the kidney cells called the sting
pathway. It doesn't sing well, but it'll
really get your kidneys riled up. Now,
one way to deal with this is to clamp
down on the sting pathway. And the
researchers do exactly that, literally
cutting out the sting pathway and then
measuring kidney function. The lower the
bars, the better the kidneys are
functioning. The red condition is the
sting pathway knockout. Clearly, there's
a significant improvement in kidney
function. But these data along with
others do not indicate a complete rescue
of the kidney function. So that means
that this leaking of DNA from
mitochondria and the loss of TFAM itself
have alternate ways of disrupting the
kidney and causing chaos. So why not
address that and work on encouraging
TFAM? Well, in fact, there are multiple
things that we can do to support TFAM
and reduce our chances of kidney failure
from leaking mitochondria, including a
supplement that's been through the
ringer a few times. And in fact, if
you're interested in learning more on
how to improve kidney health, including
a different longevity supplements
effects and how the kidneys dilate from
Tfam insufficiency and even going into
how sting works. Check out the full
version of this video that you're
watching. It's part of the Physionic
Insiders. Yep, the one linked in the
description. Oh, you also get all this
stuff, private insider podcasts, live
sessions with me, weekly articles, and
more. But you know who's counting? Like
I said, links in the description. So,
what are four things that we can do to
support TFAN production as well as
overall kidney health? I'll go over the
most general to the most specific. The
first thing is exercise. I realize
that's awfully generic and you want
something like the kidney blaster 4000
ketone that you have to snort up your
nose, but the reality is exercise
directly stimulates TFAM potently
throughout the body. To be clear, I
haven't seen any good measurements in
kidney. So there is an assumption here,
but exercise has the most generalized
positive impact on TFM and it does
improve kidney health as a whole. The
second is blood pressure control. There
is evidence that TFAM is reduced with
high blood pressure and even more
poignantly high blood pressure harms
kidney function and health. So if it's
through exercise, nutrition or making a
deal with the devil, lowering and
maintaining a normal blood pressure,
which is currently around 120 over 80.
The third is managing your potassium and
sodium. Really, it's the balance between
the two. Usually people consume far more
sodium than they do potassium. So first
simply tracking the consumption of both
over three days and then introducing
more of one or the other through rich
foods or by supplementation can have
direct powerful impact on the kidneys. I
have plenty of content on that if you
want more specifics. I'll add the links
for you. Fourth, and most specifically,
it's a supplement that's taken quite
some heat in the longevity world for
potentially not working as once
believed. However, that doesn't mean
that it's useless. And in fact, there
are studies in humans that indicate
effectiveness at improving kidney
function. And we believe it may increase
TFAM. The molecule is rveratrol. Its
effects are apparently present even in
people with healthy kidneys, but it is
even more effective in people with high
blood sugar. So we know that low TFAM
levels in the kidney leads to
significant kidney damage and death and
cysts and inflammation and need I go on.
We know that it's directly implicated
and we have some evidence although I
would want to see more that people with
poor kidney function have low TAM
levels. So assuming improving TFAM could
help our kidney function, we can do a
number of things to either directly
target TFAM or generally improve kidney
health. Exercise, maintain normal blood
pressure, keep an eye on the balance
between potassium and sodium intake. And
if you're into supplements, resveratrol
has some evidence indicating it works at
improving kidney and tfam function and
abundance, respectively. And among the
things to keep an eye on related to your
kidney health is what happens when
kidney health declines and what happens
to your arteries. I covered that and a
few more ways of improving kidney health
right